Maurice Nicoll papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Maurice Nicoll papers
1914-1996
MS 1348
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
8.02
(15 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, writings, research materials, scrapbooks and photographs documenting Maurice Nicoll's involvement with the ideas of P. D. Ouspensky and G. I. Gurdjieff. Included are manuscripts of an unpublished novel and short stories, seven scrapbooks, and a copy of Nicoll's five volume work Psychological Commentaries on the Teaching of G. I. Gurdjieff and P. D. Ouspensky. The scrapbooks contain clippings and photographs showing Gurdjieff with his group at the Prieuré Fontainbleu, as well as Nicoll's group which he formed in London. Three of the scrapbooks contain quotations from Gurdjieff's All and Everything with accompanying artwork, probably by a disciple of Nicoll's.
Nicoll, Maurice, 1884-1953
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the estate of Muriel Oldham, 1982; and Lewis Creed, 1993-1997, and 2006.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Maurice Nicoll, a psychologist, received his B.A., M.B., and B.C. degrees from Cambridge. He served as a medical officer for nervous system injuries at Empire Hospital, was a lecturer in medical psychology at Birmingham University, and was a member of the editorial staff of the Journal of Neurology and Psychopathology. Nicoll was the author of Psychological Commentaries on the Teaching of G. I. Gurdjieff and P. D. Ouspensky.
Scope and Contents
The Maurice Nicoll Papers serve as an interesting complement to the papers in the already sizeable P.D. Ouspensky Memorial Collection and illustrate the dissemination of the mystical teachings of Ouspensky and G. I. Gurdjieff in Britain.
Nicoll, a psychologist, had been a student of Carl Jung, and in the collection (folders 1 & 14) there are letters from Jung and his wife discussing their relationship with Nicoll. After joining an Ouspensky study group in London Nicoll became interested in the work of Gurdjieff and spent a year (circa 1922) at his institute at Fontainbleau, France. The Nicoll Papers contain two scrapbooks (f. 22 & 23) from the period; they were compiled by J. deForest Thompson who was at the institute as a young man with his mother, Mrs. Page. The scrapbooks contain interesting photographs of the institute and of Nicoll and Gurdjieff. There are also two handwritten letters addressed to Mrs. Page by Ouspensky. The papers contain a few other items specifically related to Ouspensky and Gurdjieff, including notes on Ouspensky's lectures and a photograph of him in India (folder 18) and the prospectus for Gurdjieff's Institute for the Harmonious Development of Man, notes on his lectures, and a copy of his funeral service (folder 19).
Nicoll formed his own group in London and later during World War lI, organized centers for carrying on the Teaching. A scrapbook (folder 20) contains photographs of Nicoll and his group at Tye-Ponds, 1935-40, and at Great Amwell House, 1946-53. The papers also contain a printed copy of his major work, Psychological Commentaries on the Teaching of G.I. Gurdjieff and P. D. Ouspensky.
For many years Mrs. Beryl Pogson was Nicoll's secretary, and many of these papers seem to have been kept by her or other members of the group at the Maurice Nicoll Free Library at the "Dicker". Pogson wrote a biography of Nicoll, compiled the scrapbook of photographs of the "Dicker" (folder 21), and may have been responsible for creating the three scrapbooks of artwork (folders 24-26) illustrating quotations from Gurdjieff's All and Everything. The papers also contain a few scattered items written by other members of Nicoll's group and some reference materials from the shelves of the library at the "Dicker".
The papers were received by the Yale Library in 1982, along with several hundred volumes, from Muriel Oldham. (Mrs. Oldham's husband had been a Nicoll student and had taken over the Nicoll library after Nicoll's death in 1953.) The volumes were received for the general collection in Sterling Library, but amongst them were the scrapbooks, writing, photographs; and pieces of correspondence now comprising the Maurice Nicoll Papers.
Psychologists; Gurdjieff, Georges Ivanovitch, 1872-1949; Nicoll, Maurice, 1884-1953; Pogson, Beryl, 1895-; Uspenskiĭ, P. D. (Petr Demʹi︠a︡novich), 1878-1947
- Original Accession, Circa 1914-1994
  - Materials of Dr. Nicoll
    - Correspondence, 1950, 1953, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "Pelican Hotel": TMs for unpublished novel, Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "Stories": TMs for unpublished short stories, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Psychological Commentaries on the Teaching of C.I. Gurdjieff and P.D. Ouspensky, vol. 1, 2, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Psychological Commentaries on the Teaching of C.I. Gurdjieff and P.D. Ouspensky, vol. 3-5, 1949, 1955, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
    - "Index to Psychological Commentaries ", Undated (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
    - "A Simple Explanation of Work Ideas", Undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - "Extracts from Dr. Nicoll's Diary in Connection with P.D. Ouspensky", Undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Tresor Hermetique: annotated by Nicoll with AMs "The Emerald Table of Hermes", Circa 1914 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Notes on Dr. Nicoll's meetings, 1944-1951 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Unpublished paper, Undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - "Introduction to a Scientic Paper" [by Nicoll?], 1944 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Materials of Beryl and Midge Pogson, 1953-1966,undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Materials of other Members of Dr. Nicoll's group, 1956, 1963,1981,1993, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Materials of other members of Dr. Nicoll's group, Undated (Box 4, Folder 16-17)
  - Materials about P.D. Ouspensky, 1922-1936, undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Materials about Gurdjieff, 1921-1966, undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Scrapbook
    - Photographs of Dr. Nicoll's Group, 1946-1953 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Photographs of the Dicker, Circa 1966-1976 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Photographs and letters relating to Mr. Gurdjieff and his group at the Prieuré, Fontainbleau, 1922-1923, 1933 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Press cuttings printed at the time about Mr. Gurdjieff and his group at the Prieuré, Fontainbleau, 1923 (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - All and Everything First Picture Book, Undated (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - All and Everything Second Picture Book, Undated (Box 7, Folder 25)
    - All and Everything Third Picture Book, Undated (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Books relating to the teachings of G. I. Gurdjieff, P. D. Ouspensky, and Maurice Nicoll, written and/or compiled by Beryl Pogson and others
    - Commentary on the Fourth Gospel, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 27)
    - Work Talks in Brighton, 1963-1966, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 27)
    - More Work Talks, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 27)
    - Work Talks at The Dicker, 1966, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 27)
    - Unforgotten Fragments, 1994 (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - Books written by or about Beryl Pogson
    - Beryl Chassereau Pogson: a biographical foreword for In The East My Pleasure Lies compiled by Lewis Creed, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 28)
    - In The East My Pleasure Lies and other Esoteric Interpretations of Plays by William Shakespeare, by Beryl Pogson, 1994 (Box 9, Folder 28)
- Additional Material, 1940-1994; Accession 1994-M-091
  Scope and Contents
  Also includes Accessions 1995-M-087 and 1995-M-108
  - Books relating to the teachings of G. I. Gurdjieff, P. D. Ouspensky, and Maurice Nicoll, written and/or compiled by Beryl Pogson and others (early undated editions)
    - Commentary on the Fourth Gospel (2 copies) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Work Talks in Brighton, 1963 to 1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - More Work Talks, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Work-Talks at the Dicker, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Books written/compiled by Beryl Pogson
    - Romeo and Juliet: an Esoteric Interpretation, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Three Plays by Shakespeare: an Esoteric Interpretation, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Royalty of Nature: A Commentary on Shakespeare's History-Plays, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - The Choice (2 copies), Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Curiosities in Literature: a Fragment of an Unfinished Anthology, compiled by Beryl Pogson, commentaries by Maurice Nicoll, Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Research material for the biographical-foreword of I n the East My Pleasure Lies, by Beryl Pogson, 1955, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Incomplete drafts: pages of writings and notes of Maurice Nicoll, Beryl Pogson, and other members of Nicoll's group, 1940s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
  - writings of others
    - "Gurdjieff, Ouspensky and Nicoll - A Living Teaching?" by T. I. Casswell, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "Memories of EQ and Eve," by Louisa Creed, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "In Memory of E. Q. Nicholson": memorial service, 1992 November 4 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "A Note on the story of Jacob," by Laurie Goodman, Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Vibrations, by Muriel Farmer Oldham, Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Words on the Work: by a Worker Talking to Other Workers, anonymous, Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - The Work Life: Based on Teachings of G. I. Gurdjieff, P. D. Ouspensky and Maurice Nicoll, by Beryl Pogson, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    General
    (Accession 1995-M-087)
  - Centenary Fragments, by Beryl Pogson, compiled by Lewis Creed, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    (Accession 1995-M-108)
- Additonal material, 1916-1987; Accession 1995-M-123
  Also includes Accession 1995-M-125
  - Incomplete drafts, pages of writings and notes, of Maurice Nicoll, Beryl Pogson, and other members of Nicoll's group, 1930s-1975, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Memoriam program for Beryl Pogson, 1967 February 5 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Photographs, 1916-1976 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Maurice Nicoll: A Portrait, by Beryl Pogson, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Additional Material, 1965-1995; Accession 1995-M-186
  Also includes Accession 1996-M-006 and 1996-M-067
  - Additional Material, Accession 1995-M-186
    - Diogenes in Time and Tide (1955-1960), 1995 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Diogenes may have been W.J. Brown M.P., Independent Member of Parliament for Rugby, student of P.D. Ouspensky; original newspaper articles accompany publication.
    - Ouspensky study group meeting notes [recorded by Beryl Pogson], 1963 May 7 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "Shakespeare and the 'Supernatural' -II", Light [by Beryl Pogson], 1965 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Holiday greeting cards of Maurice and Catherine Nicoll, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Additional Material, Accession 1996-M-006
    - Practical Work Tasks [by Beryl Pogson, compiled by Lewis Creed from meeting notes between 1960-1966], 1995 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Additional Material, Accession 1996-M-067
    - Informal Work Talks and Teachings, 1940-1950 [by Maurice Nicoll, compiled by Lewis Creed], 1995 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Additional Material, 1940-1996; Accession 1996-M-092
  Also includes Accession 1997-M-061
  - Additional Material, Accession 1996-M-092
    - "Movements, Sacred Dances and Ritual Exercises of Gurdjieff," [theater program for the Fortune Theater, London], 1952 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Personal note from Lewis Creed [description of his introduction to the work of Maurice Nicoll], 1957 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "Informal Work Talks of Dr. Nicoll," [typescript of notes on and extracts from talks given by Maurice Nicoll from 1940-1950, compiled by Lewis Creed], Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Ouspensky, P. D.
      - List of mental exercises for his pupils, 1940s (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Printed material about his burial site at Lyne, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "The Mural: the Labours of Hercules", 1957 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Typescript of the impressions of Beryl Pogson's study group on painting the mural of Hercules in the classroom at Dorton.
    - "Beryl Pogson's Centenary", 1995 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Additional Material, Accession 1997-M-061
    - Notes Taken at Meetings with Maurice Nicoll: January 18, 1934 to April 28, 1934, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Compiled by a member of Nicoll's group; typescript and publication.
- Additional material, 1962, undated; Accession 1997-M-108
  - "The Choice," compiled by Beryl Pogson, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Diagrams from Dr. Nicoll's Room", Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Photocopies of diagrams pertaining to the universe.
  - Photographs
    - Art works, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - The Dicker, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Includes two drawings of residence.
    - Nicoll, Maurice, Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Pogson, Beryl, 1962, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Theobald, Minnie, Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Additional material, Undated; Accession 2006-M-080
  - "Some Impressions of Dorton, Christmas 1956.", Undated (Box 1)